I've been meaning to cover this topic
for some time but the topics are never
ending and I'm glad I waited because I
stumbled across an interview with
physician Dr Casey means discussing the
very same topic so why not meld her
perspective with the science that I
expected to cover anyway so what is one
simple thing the simplest of things that
will begin your metabolically healthy
life let's listen in let's talk about a
few of these things that can improve um
glucose disposal um and mitochondrial
function uh mitophagy the removal of of
dead or dysfunctional mitochondria so
they can be replaced um let's talk about
the walking one first you said 7,000
steps a day I don't track my steps um
what are we really talking about there
we're talking about taking the stairs
and trying to walk as much as possible
maybe we like if we were going to just
give like a really crude prescription
you're a doctor so you can prescribe
things um what would you tell people to
do like how many short walks per day is
is it like three is it five is um what
are we talking I would say up I mean at
at least three I would say aiming for
more than that is good though there's so
so to sort of just give a sense of the
picture of walking if walking were a
pill it would be the most uh impactful
pill we've ever had in all of modern
medicine okay that's quite a statement I
don't think I disagree but I need to
reflect on that just a bit anyway why is
walking such a potent driver of Health
um there was a paper in jamama uh 6,300
participants followed
for uh 10 to 11 years and the people who
simply walked 7,000 steps per day
compared to less than that had in up to
70% lower risk of all cause mortality in
the follow-up period so not causality
but it's it's pretty incredible okay one
thing I appreciate about Dr huberman's
podcast is that he adds the references
to studies mentioned so I was bble to
find the studies that Dr mean's
references uh she mentions that people
who walk 7,000 steps per day have a 70%
reduced risk of all cause mortality and
she's absolutely right we can see that
here on the left we have three buckets
of Step count less than 7,000 between 7
and 10,000 and over 10,000 on the right
we have different models these models
represent statistical adjustments to the
data to account for possible confounding
variables for example maybe Walkers just
happen to be skinnier and that's the
real reason that mortality was reduced
so the researchers account for weight
they accounted for a lot of things I'll
offer a list if we look at the most
adjusted model model three the
researchers identify a 72% reduced
mortality risk compared to people who
walk less than 7,000 steps now I should
caution here because one problem with
these buckets is that they're a bit
crude in what they measure for example
the majority of people in the 7 to
10,000 step group could be hitting 9,000
steps and those in the sub 7,000 could
be on the extreme toward 1,000 steps we
don't have that granularity the reason I
mentioned that is because we don't
necessarily this doesn't actually tell
us if it's exactly 7,000 steps that lead
to this protective effect we only know
that it's somewhere between 7 and 10,000
steps either way the overall point
stands walking every day is a huge
benefit we'll get into why in a few
minutes they've done followup research
with slightly different numbers showing
again though like many thousands of
people uh in the study followed for
about 10 years 8,000 to 12,000 steps per
day was associated with 50 to 65% lower
uh all cause mortality and this has been
played out in many studies showing about
a 50% reduction in Alzheimer's uh
dementia obesity typee 2 diabetes
depression cancer gastric reflux just
all across the board again quite a punch
I love it so Dr means reference is
another study yet unfortunately I
couldn't track that study down because
the one posted was not the one that
she's describing it doesn't matter much
though because her point is well taken
and in fact let me take the opportunity
to point out an interesting datam from
another study interestingly according to
this study the researchers identifi that
the walking benefit is most pronounced
for people over the age of 65 and much
less potent for people under 65 we can
see that the data here indicates that if
a person walks 8,000 steps between three
and seven times per week they're
associated with significantly reduced
mortality risk compared to those who
don't achieve 8,000 even once a week
this analysis was also adjusted like the
previous study okay let's get into some
of the juicy physiology and I think the
key thing is that it's not about the
steps it's about the fact that muscle
contraction is medicine when we contract
our muscles even in a very like lowgrade
way like walking or doing a couple air
squats you know we're activating amk and
we are essentially causing that cell to
have a stimulus to push glucose channels
to the cell membrane most of the time
the glucose channels are like in
vesicles ins in little bags inside the
cells they're not on the cell membrane
so of course that's going to keep the
the glucose in your in your bloodstream
not being processed by the mitochondria
so when we think about steps it's a
proxy metric for just moving more
throughout the day there's a lot of good
information here okay so the main point
that we shouldn't Focus too too much on
the steps themselves but more so on the
general sentiment of increasing physical
activity as a whole not even necessarily
dedicated activity it can be as simple
as just getting up from your chair every
15 to 30 minutes and walking down a
hallway and back now in terms of the
physiology she's spoton movement
requires your muscle cells millions of
them to contract that contraction
requires energy and energy is supplied
in the form of fat molecules and glucose
molecules now Dr means focuses on
glucose entry into the muscle cells
through the activation of a transport
protein called glute essentially as
described in this study when the energy
levels are reduced within the muscle
cell a master protein called ampk is
activated when activated it stimulates
the movement of glute proteins to the
surface of the cell where they embed
themselves into the cell membrane in
doing so more channels more openings
exist for glucose to enter from the
blood into the cell and eventually they
get delivered to mitochondria for energy
generation if this happens many times a
day and over many years the net effect
is a better metabolic Health lower blood
sugar better muscle tone and more that
we don't have time to get into this is
further corroborated and reillustrated
in this review you can see the uh
glucose molecule moving from the blood
to the liquid between the blood and the
muscle cell it's noted as the myosite
and if the glute protein is already on
the cell membrane it allows glucose into
the cell which ultimately goes through a
metabolic pathway known as glycolysis
and eventually ends up at the
mitochondria at least in this scenario
so Dr Casey is as I mentioned spot-on so
what are the takeaways here before we
get to that there's also some data on
step intensity as in how quickly you
walk and the relationship to mortality
as well as some other nuances that come
from these two studies that we just went
over if you're so inclined I'm uh
covering more on this topic in the
extended version of this video which is
found along with all my investigations
on your health including applicable
takeaways in my premium research review
called the physionic Insiders it's found
in the description box if you're
interested I'd love to have you aboard
okay the takeaways here are pretty
simple but we'll add some numbers to it
for the number hungry folks out there
the big takeaway is that walking is a
major move pun not intended in improving
your metabolic health and protecting
yourself against all cause mortality but
you don't have to be rigid with it you
can also make sure just to move if
that's a short walk down a hallway at
work every 30 minutes or a few body
weight squats or whatever you see fit
for those more number-based we don't
actually have 100% foolproof exact
numbers but based on what we have it
seems safe that the majority of the
benefit comes in around 8,000 steps per
day so if you want a Target there it is
I cover the impact using weighted vests
while walking has on your health
including a very cool mechanism related
to your bones right here or if 8,000
steps isn't enough for you how about
taking it up a few notches right here
check this out I'll catch you over there
bye
[Music]